<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Darpan Choudhary</title>
    <link>https://darpanchoudhary.com/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://darpanchoudhary.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>MBA is (not?) important</title>
      <link>https://darpanchoudhary.com/writings/2024-11-24-mba-is-not-important/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://darpanchoudhary.com/writings/2024-11-24-mba-is-not-important/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Nov 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>The question of whether to pursue an MBA can feel overwhelming. Is it the golden ticket to career success? Or is it just a really expensive way to delay figuring out what you want to do with your life?</p>
<p>I've lived through this debate. I studied at IIM Indore for my undergraduate program (IPM) and then went straight into an MBA at IIM Ahmedabad. Looking back, I can't say the decision was perfect, but it wasn't wrong either. It was just... mine.</p>
<p>Let's talk about why an MBA might (or might not) make sense.<br>
<br></p>
<h4><strong>MBA: the &quot;safe&quot; path</strong></h4>
<p>Let's be real. Higher education is often seen as a safety net. It's less about what you learn and more about the brand value it slaps onto your CV. When I was deciding whether to do an MBA, the job market for top front-end roles in consulting and finance seemed like a gated community. Without the &quot;MBA&quot; badge, you weren't even invited to apply.</p>
<p>There's a reason for this. The sheer competition forces recruiters to use shortcuts. An MBA from a tier-1 college is shorthand for:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>You can survive grueling schedules</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You've passed through some of the toughest academic filters</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You're likely to have at least some polish in a client-facing communication</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>But here's the thing: an MBA isn't necessarily about learning. It's about signaling. It's a way of saying, <em>&quot;Hey, I'm credible. Take me seriously.&quot;</em></p>
<p>In many companies, especially in consulting and finance, an MBA often becomes essential to access higher-responsibility roles. In my case, one of the reasons I chose IIM Ahmedabad was future-proofing. My company hires exclusively from IIMA and ISB for entry-level roles, with rare exceptions like LSE and IIMB. Small team sizes mean they focus on candidates with proven credentials, and I wanted to position myself for those opportunities. For me, it was about maximizing the likelihood of long-term career success.<br>
<br></p>
<h4><strong>Survivorship bias in entrepreneurship</strong></h4>
<p>Now, let's address the elephant in the room: entrepreneurship. It's often seen as the cooler, more independent alternative to the MBA. Be your own boss. Build something that's yours. Skip the grind of a classroom and go straight to the action.</p>
<p>Before I go any further, let me say this: I have nothing against entrepreneurs. It's the bold, crazy, and audacious who change the world. In fact, I would love to start something of my own someday. These are just my reflections from when I was trying to decide whether to pursue an MBA or take a different path.</p>
<p>Here's what you don't hear enough: opinions online about entrepreneurship are often swayed by the financial backgrounds of those advocating for it. Many success stories involve founders who had family money, connections, or the luxury of failing without catastrophic consequences. The narrative that anyone can make it big can feel empowering, but it glosses over the fact that <em>not everyone starts from the same place.</em></p>
<p>Entrepreneurship is about betting big, and while the upside can be life-changing, the downside can be equally harsh. For every startup that takes off, nine others fail. Choosing to pursue an MBA, on the other hand, is less about hitting the jackpot and more about stacking the odds in your favor. It's not the path to outsized outcomes, but it offers better protection against the downside. It's like choosing a fixed deposit over the stock market. The stock market (entrepreneurship) can give you extraordinary returns, but it's volatile, risky, and heavily dependent on timing. The fixed deposit (MBA) won't make you rich (relatively) overnight, but it ensures steady growth and safeguards your financial and career stability.<br>
<br></p>
<h4><strong>The Road Not Taken</strong></h4>
<p>Would I have been better off working for a few years before doing my MBA? Maybe. A few years of work experience often makes the MBA experience richer, as you know what you're solving for. At the same time, my undergraduate program (IPM) was relatively new back in 2018-2021, and there weren't many success stories to guide me. My network was small, and I didn't have access to the kind of mentorship that might've helped me take a different path.</p>
<p>So, I went for the MBA. It was a safe choice, yes, but it also worked out. I learned a lot, grew as a person, and landed my dream job. Was it the only way? No. Was it the best way for me at that time? Probably.<br>
<br></p>
<h4><strong>So, is it worth it?</strong></h4>
<p>The answer depends on you. If you're clear about your goals and can access the networks and opportunities you need without an MBA, then maybe it's not necessary. But if you're looking for a reset, a launchpad, or a way to fast-track your career, an MBA (especially from a top school) can still be a solid investment.</p>
<p>For me, the MBA wasn't a magic solution, but it was a meaningful chapter. It helped me grow, build connections, and step into a world I might not have accessed otherwise. If you're considering it, don't just think about whether it's worth the money. Think about whether it's worth your time, your energy, and your dreams. Because at the end of the day, the MBA is a tool. What you build with it is up to you.</p>
]]></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elite Capture</title>
      <link>https://darpanchoudhary.com/writings/2025-10-09-elite-capture/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://darpanchoudhary.com/writings/2025-10-09-elite-capture/</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>While reading Noam Chomsky's <em>Who Rules the World?</em> I came across an idea about the gap that exists between the demands of the commons and policies implemented by politicians in the United States. It's commonly known as elite capture, when those with wealth end up shaping the rules in their favour. The idea stuck with me because it is not unique to America. Every democracy seems to suffer from some version of it. What changes is the way it works.<br>
<br></p>
<p>The commons are consistently ignored, as politicians are driven to support only the needs of the elite. This happens because elites, who have amassed disproportionate levels of wealth, are the only ones who can bankroll these politicians during elections. These politicians then adopt policies that enrich the elite, leaving out the commons, and the cycle continues.<br>
<br></p>
<p>Some examples of these contradictions are easy to spot. Climate policy often reflects the interests of Big Oil. Budgets protect defence contractors while cutting Medicaid. Other relevant examples include downsizing the budgets of important regulatory bodies like the SEC and the FDA, and repeated tax cuts that disproportionately benefit the wealthy. You can see how this works in the case of Jeff Yass, the billionaire with a big stake in TikTok. He happened to be the top Republican donor in 2024. Quite predictably, Trump eventually reversed course on banning TikTok after meeting Yass. <span class="footnote-ref">[<a href="#f1">1</a>]</span><br></p>
<p><img src="/images/palantir.png" alt="palantir stare"></p>
<p>The credit for elite capture in the US goes to its reserve currency status. Global savings started flowing into the US, as the US dollar was considered the safest currency. <span class="footnote-ref">[<a href="#f2">2</a>]</span> This caused a massive wave of financialization across the US economy. Finance began pulling resources away from other areas of the economy. Manufacturing was outsourced as it could not compete with the financial industry for capital or labour. The financialization led to a massive concentration of wealth within the finance industry, kick-starting the cycle of quid pro quo between Wall Street and policymakers. The effect is visible in the extreme wealth inequality: the US had a Gini coefficient of 41.8 in 2023. <span class="footnote-ref">[<a href="#f3">3</a>]</span><br>
<br></p>
<p>Seeing how finance shaped politics in the US made me wonder how things look in a place like India, where the economy and politics work differently. We never had that kind of financial dominance, and our politics never gave money the same freedom.<br>
<br></p>
<p>For all the criticism that socialist schemes get in India, I think we've ended up in an odd kind of equilibrium. It slows us down in some ways but protects us in others. Money that could have gone into education, research, or industry ends up funding welfare schemes, which limits growth. But the same welfare politics also stops the rich from taking over completely. The elite still have influence, but mostly in getting contracts or access to natural resources. They haven't been able to touch welfare spending. So, we've ended up in a strange balance where the country doesn't grow as fast as it could, but the power stays a little more evenly spread.<br>
<br></p>
<p>It is an equilibrium because if any party chooses to tilt towards the wealthy too much, there is a high probability of them losing elections. The other party, which offers more socialist benefits, is likely to win. Elites still lobby, but their influence remains confined. They can shape who gets a licence or a contract, but not whether the poor get food or healthcare.<br>
<br></p>
<p><br><br></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<h2>Footnotes</h2>
<p><a name="f1">[1]</a> https://www.reuters.com/world/us/republican-hedge-fund-owner-tiktok-investor-yass-emerges-top-donor-us-election-2024-03-21</p>
<p><a name="f2">[2]</a> This goes against the theory widely accepted by the economists which claims that agents of capitalism would invest in areas where the highest return per unit of investment instead of being strictly risk averse.</p>
<p><a name="f3">[3]</a> https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SI.POV.GINI?locations=US</p>
</div>
<p><br><br></p>
<div class="thanks">
Thank you to Muskan and ChatGPT for taking the time to read and provide feedback on early drafts of this essay.
</div>]]></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t let AI write everything for you</title>
      <link>https://darpanchoudhary.com/writings/2025-10-16-dont-let-ai-write-everything-for-you/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://darpanchoudhary.com/writings/2025-10-16-dont-let-ai-write-everything-for-you/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>I have been trying to get back into writing regularly. I ran into more problems than I expected, mostly because I've relied so heavily on generative AI for the last two years. Once you get used to writing with AI, it's hard to go back. I still use AI, but I have limited its use to analysing whether the essay is unified and reads well. Before generative AI was a thing, it was much easier for me to come up with an early draft and then edit it myself.<br><br></p>
<p>The reason is simple: our brains are lazy and enjoy taking shortcuts while thinking. AI generated writing is a form of shortcut for the brain as we don't have to mentally go through the iterative process of thinking and writing. It is also the reason why well-thought-out analyses are as rare as hen's teeth because the brain tends to fall back to heuristics or generalisations to reduce its energy usage. <span class="footnote-ref">[<a href="#f1">1</a>]</span><br><br></p>
<p>It may seem harmless, but the problem with extended use of AI for writing is that it makes you dumber. Writing is an essential part of human activity that trains the brain to visualize and solve problems. It engages multiple areas of your brain to</p>
<ul>
<li>come up with an idea given a specific context,</li>
<li>outline your goal you want to achieve through this writing,</li>
<li>understand the target audience, and</li>
<li>find a coherent way to put your thoughts into words.<br></li>
</ul>
<p>What you're really doing, without noticing, is outsourcing those steps to an LLM. The areas of the brain that are engaged during those steps are also used for problem solving, decision making and learning new habits. Over time, as your brain adjusts to this reduced activity, it loses some of its ability to carry out these tasks efficiently.<br></p>
<p><img src="/images/0iqcat.png" alt="0 iq cat"></p>
<p>Earlier this year, MIT conducted a (not yet peer reviewed) study on the cognitive cost of using LLMs to write an essay. 54 subjects which were divided into three groups: one with access to ChatGPT, one using Google Search, and one with no external tools. The study was conducted over the course of four months and as time passed the ChatGPT group performed increasingly poor as compared control group without access to any external tools. ChatGPT group had the lowest brain engagement and weakest memory recall. They even faced difficulty in quoting their own work (that was generated with the &quot;help&quot; of ChatGPT). So, the more you let your AI do your thinking, the less capable you become of thinking at all. <span class="footnote-ref">[<a href="#f2">2</a>]</span><br><br></p>
<p>The short-term benefit of saving time with the use of AI might not be worth the long-term damage to your cognitive abilities unless you can replace writing with an equally engaging activity. This is even more damaging for the younger users as it could significantly hinder their cognitive growth.<br><br></p>
<p>I'm not trying to disparage the efficiency in work that is brought on by AI. There is no doubt that it has improved my productivity significantly. The problem arises when you can’t write a sentence without asking it to think for you. As sad as it sounds but you need to make a conscious effort to not give in to the temptation of letting AI write everything for you.</p>
<p><br><br><br><br></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<h2>Footnotes</h2>
<p><a name="f1">[1]</a> This is one of the brain operating principles that I came across while attending a elective called Neuroscience and Consumer Behaviour. It was taught by Prof. Arvind Sahay at IIMA. If you're interested in learning more about this, I strongly suggest you to read &quot;Brands and the Brain: How to Use Neuroscience to Create Impactful Brands&quot;</p>
<p><a name="f2">[2]</a> https://www.media.mit.edu/publications/your-brain-on-chatgpt</p>
</div>
<p><br><br></p>
<div class="thanks">
Thanks to ChatGPT for taking the time to read and provide feedback on early drafts of this essay.
</div>]]></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trap of universal basic income</title>
      <link>https://darpanchoudhary.com/writings/2025-11-13-universal-basic-income-trap/</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://darpanchoudhary.com/writings/2025-11-13-universal-basic-income-trap/</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Over the past few days there has been a growing interest around the idea of universal basic income (UBI). Lately, at least in the West, a lot of people on X (twitter) seem to like the idea. The idea is being flirted with by several political leaders and influential people in general. Elon Musk, Sam Altman, Jack Dorsey and Marc Benioff are among the many vocal supporters of universal basic income. There have been numerous studies by economists and pilots to understand the economic impact.<br><br></p>
<p>The reason for writing this essay is not to talk about the economic implications of UBI or how it will be funded but to hypothesise about the consequences based on the incentives of the players involved in this reform.<br><br></p>
<p>I think of it as a three-player system: business, government, and society. Over the years, we've seen that society is unable to coordinate in the same way that businesses and government can. I feel the reason for this is that the motivations for every person or family unit are extremely varied. There does not seem to be a clear singular goal for a society. On the other hand, businesses and government have a clear mandate to maximise profits and consolidate power barring a few exceptions. And in a capitalistic regime, consolidating power and maximizing profits go hand in hand. I have written about this in detail in another essay titled &quot;Elite Capture&quot;. <span class="footnote-ref">[<a href="#f1">1</a>]</span> But broadly speaking, capitalism leads to concentration of wealth with businesses, and it is then utilised to lobby the government. Lobbying allows the political parties to fund their election campaigns and remain in power while businesses receive special treatment from the ruling government disregarding societal interests. <span class="footnote-ref">[<a href="#f2">2</a>]</span><br><br></p>
<p>This matters even more with UBI. For years the labour constraint on growth has been one of the few levers society has in its favour. Businesses and government alike try to shape the opinion of the society to benefit themselves. There have been enough examples of polarisation, exploiting insecurities, targeting vulnerable populations and the list goes on.<br><br></p>
<p>The typical argument peddled by the influential tech leaders is that once AI enabled automation is prevalent in the industry, there will be no need for any of us to do work. Our lives won't revolve around our jobs, and we'll be free to pursue hobbies such as writing poetry or painting. It's an interesting shift in narrative coming from people who spent decades preaching hustle culture because it benefited them greatly in the past. If you step back, you notice that stories like this often serve the interests of those telling them. I would like to run through a chain of thought to show what could be the real motivator for pushing for UBI.<br></p>
<p><img src="/images/cap-wojak.png" alt="wojak"></p>
<p>With the rise of AI, a lot of jobs will be automated away, and there will be a wave of layoffs. That alone could turn the majority against capitalism. To make those layoffs acceptable, the government will have to cushion the blow with UBI. So, you'll start seeing a rosy picture of UBI in the media, much of it sponsored by people who benefit from automation.<br><br></p>
<p>The government will support it too. If they control the source of income, they control compliance. And once society no longer plays a meaningful role in the economy, why would groups whose goal is to maximize profit and consolidate power care about its rights? Simply stated, introduction of UBI could potentially remove any remaining accountability on businesses and governments and reduce whatever bargaining power society has left.<br><br></p>
<p>None of this is inevitable. It only sounds dystopian because of the incentives we have now: a system where power concentrates upward and labour constraint is going away. If those incentives changed, the outcome could change with them. But as things stand, UBI feels like a way to increase the dependency of the society on the governments and businesses.</p>
<p><br><br><br><br></p>
<div class="footnotes">
<h2>Footnotes</h2>
<p><a name="f1">[1]</a> https://darpanchoudhary.com/writings/2025-10-09-elite-capture</p>
<p><a name="f2">[2]</a> This isn't an argument for communism or against capitalism. I'm critical of the extreme, financialized version of capitalism seen in the US. Capitalism works better than the alternatives, but it still needs a balancing act to keep it from running off the rails.</p>
</div>
<p><br><br></p>
<div class="thanks">
Thanks to ChatGPT for taking the time to read and provide feedback on early drafts of this essay.
</div>]]></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>